Edward A. Khairallah Papers
© 2006 University of Connecticut
Edward A. Khairallah Papers.
undated, 1958-1996
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Khairallah, Edward A.
11.7 linear feet
The collection contains the professional papers of Edward A. Khairallah, Professor of Molecular and Cell Biology, at the University of Connecticut.
MSS19980305
Biography
A professor of Molecular and Cell Biology at the University of Connecticut. Dr. Khairallah died in 1996.
Scope and Content
The collection contains the professional papers of Dr. Khairallah and includes reports, grants, class materials, publications, papers, presentations, articles and similar materials pertaining to his research interests.
Arrangement
The collection has only been inventoried at the box level at this time.
Series I: Papers ( undated, 1958-1996 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Khairallah, Edward A.
Organizations:
University of Connecticut.
Subjects:
University of Connecticut--Faculty--Professional and personal papers.; Molecular biology--Study and teaching.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Notebooks.; Publications.; Photographs.; Administrative Records.; Minutes.; Manuscripts.; Galley proofs.; Typescripts.; Photocopies.; Notes.
Occupations:
Professor.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection at this time. Upon request for access, the boxes will be reviewed to determine appropriate status of individual folders.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Dr. Lamia Khairallah in 1997.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Papers, undated, 1958-1996
  - (Box 1)
    - APAP Correspondence
      - "Effect of Oxygen Deficiency on Acetaminophen Toxicity in Mice"
      - Related correspondence
    - Annual Report, 1993
      - Department of Molecular and Cell Biology Annual Report, 1992-1993
      - Cover page and abstract (p. 286) from the Journal of Basic & Clinical Physiology and Pharmacology, vol 3., (supplement), 1992 July
    - Biochemistry Program, 1994-1996
    - Biology Brochure, undated
    - Biotechnology Center, 1993
      - (Correspondence to Vice-President Thomas Tighe, Provost, re: funding, 1993 Fall
    - Blanchard, Kerry, undated
      - "Pulmonary activation of CMT and increased glutathione synthesis"
    - Charlie, undated
      - (research proposal re: salicylic acid and apoptosis [no additional name given])
    - China, 1996
      - (Citizen Ambassador Program of People to People International)
    - Department Affairs - with subfolder, University Plans, undated
      - (Correspondence and documents re: development of: College of Liberal Arts and Sciences Biological Sciences Group - later Department of Molecular and Cell Biology; Institute of Cellular Biology)
    - Env. Tox. Program, undated
      - (Correspondence/information re. environmental science at UConn)
    - Invitation to write a chapter [for John Walker's Methods in Molecular Biology series], undated
      - (Correspondence, Dept. of Molecular Biotechnology, University of Washington)
    - MCB 334 - Aptosis, 1996
    - NESOT (Northeast Chapter, Society of Toxicology] conference abstracts, 1995
    - Nutritional sciences, Department of, undated
    - Pete Oates, undated
      - Peter J. Oates: "Gastric Blood Flow and Mucosal Defense" [chapter]
      - Correspondence, curriculum vitae
    - Physiology Center - Grants, undated
      - "Acetaminophen Hepatotoxicity and Cellular Homeostasis"
      - Proposal to National Science Foundation
    - Reproductive Toxicology, undated
      - Correspondence, Mobil Oil Corp. Dept. of Environmental Affairs and Toxicology
      - Proposal to University of Connecticut Research Foundation
      - College of Agriculture and Natural Resources
    - Searches - (molecular/cellular biologist search candidates, 1994 Fall
    - Society of Toxicology - Abstracts and Other Information, undated
    - Toxicology Program, undated
    - Colleagues, undated
      - Crain, Richard C.
      - Giardina, Charles
      - Jim Stevens - (Dr. Sam A. Bruschi)
      - Kelly, Judith
    - Students, undated
      - Cara Ebeling
      - Hamid Boulares
      - Lei Liu
      - Lucas, Angela
      - Makowski, Gregory
      - Ramsby, Melinda
    - Loose materials/articles/correspondence, undated
      - Prospectus -- Graduate Studies in Biochemistry and Biophysics at UConn; Graduate Studies: Molecular and Cell Biology at UConn
  - (Box 2)
    - Loose materials/articles/correspondence, undated, 1992
      - Northeast Chapter, Society of Toxicology: Symposium on Reproductive/Developmental Toxicology and Poster Session, 1992 October
    - Abstract Form, Society of Toxicology Annual Meeting, 1996
    - Biochem Program, 1991-1994
    - Corcoran, George B., University of New Mexico College of Pharmacy, Correspondence, undated
    - Gordon Research Conference '96 - Lysosomes, 1996
    - Holme, Jorn A., Statens Institut for Folkehelse, Correspondence, undated
    - Honors and University Scholars Program, undated
    - Unidentified Correspondence, undated
    - Scholars Day - Letter to President Hartley, 1995
    - Seminar Series, MCB 393, 1995
    - UConn Open House, 1995
    - Individual faculty record, 1995
    - Grant Application Files, undated, 1967-1996
      - Grant Progress Report" [NIH Grant #R01-AM-15919-02], including duplicate folder, "Starvation and the Regulation of Protein Degradation
      - Grant Proposal to UConn Research Foundation, "The Role of Lysosomes in Protein Degradation,", 1973
      - Magnesium Project
        - UConn Research Foundation, "Studies on Protein Turnover and Magnesium Deficiency,", 1967
        - Related correspondence (N.I.H., U.C. Davis College of Agriculture)
        - Correspondence, Ruth Schwartz, New York State College of Human Ecology, Cornell University
      - Mel - Heterophagy
        - Damon Runyon Memorial Fund for Cancer Research: "Regulation of Protein Degradation in Normal and Neoplastic Liver,", 1973
        - UConn Research Foundation: "Nutritional Control of Hepatic Protein Turnover and Autophagy" ["Protein Turnover and the Mechanisms of Autophagy"]; "The Role of Lysosomes in Protein Degradation,", 1973, 1978
      - N.I.H. 5.171-000-06-0202-01-602/01-791
        - Dept. of Health, Education and Welfare: "Starvation and Regulation of Protein Degradation,", 1972
        - Draft, "Determination of Absolute Rates of Protein Degradation in Rat Liver"
      - Progress Report on Grant 1991-1996 With Steve Cohen, APAP toxicity
      - Research Foundation, Cysteinyl glycine, 1977
        - UConn Research Foundation: "Implications of Amino Acid Compartmentation in the Regulation of Protein Synthesis and Degradation"
      - Research Foundation Grants, 1995-1996
        - "Cellular Responses to Acetaminophen Covalent Binding" (Interim Funding)
        - "Cellular Significance of the Translocation of 58-kDa Acetaminophen Binding Protein into the Nucleus" (Interim Funding)
      - Steven D. Cohen, 1983
        - Dept. of Health and Human Services, "Mechanisms of Acetaminophen Hepatoxicity"
    - Publication/manuscript files, undated
      - Airhart, Judith and Khairallah, "Determination of Absolute Rates of Protein Degradation in Rat Liver"
      - Correspondence with Life Sciences Journal, The Biochemical Journal, and Nature Re: "Post-Transcriptional Control of Rat Liver Phosphoenolpyruvate Carboxykinase", Benson R. Treadow, E.A. Khairallah, 1973
    - Publication of "Compartmentation of Free Amino Acids for Protein Biosynthesis II: Influence of Dirunal Changes in the Hepatic Amino Acid Concentration on the Composition of the Precursor Pool Charging Aminoacyl-tRNA" in The Biochemical Journal, and related manuscripts/correspondence, 1976
      - Publication of "Identification of a 54-kDa Mitochondrial Acetaminophen-Binding Protein as Aldehyde Deydrogenase", Judith S. Landin, et al, in Toxicology and Applied Pharmacology, 1996
      - Publication of "Assessment of Protein Turnover by Valyl-tRNA in Perfused Rat Liver and Its Relation to Amino Acid Compartmentation", Glenn E. Mortimore et al, in Journal of Biological Chemistry, 1975
      - Manuscripts/correspondence in re. Publication of "Clofibrate Pretreatment Diminishes Acetaminophen Selective Covalent Binding and Hepatotoxicity", Jose E. Manautou, et al, in Toxicology and Applied Pharmacology, 1994
      - Correspondence and final publication of "Comparative Toxicity: Mechanistic Studies on Acetaminophen Action In Vitro and In Vivo in Various Species Including Man", Charles A. Tyson, et al, in Alternative Methods in Toxicology, 1991
      - "Evidence Against Deacetylation and for Cytochrome P450-Mediated Activation in Acetaminophen-Induced Nephrotoxicity in the CD-1 Mouse", Susan G. Emeigh Hart, et al, 1989, published in Toxicology and Applied Pharmacology, 1996
      - Publication of "Differential Detergent Fractionation of Isolated Heptocytes: Biochemical, Immunochemical and Two Dimensional Gel Electrophoretic Characterization of Cytoskeletal and Noncytoskeletal Compartments", Ramsby, Melinda L., et al, in Electrophoresis: An International Journal, 1993-1994
    - Student files, undated
      - "Bartolone II" (drafts, "Immunochemical Analysis of Acetaminophen Covalent Binding to Proteins: Partial Characterization of the Major Acetaminophen-Binding Liver Proteins", 1987
      - Bruno, Mary K.
      - Hong, Mira
      - Navarro, Caren (incl. publication of data report, "Genes encoding the acetaminophen and selenium binding proteins map to mouse Chromosome 3", Navarro et al, in Mammalian Genome)
      - Puchalsky, David R.
  - (Box 3)
    - Course files, undated
      - Apoptosis - handouts
      - Course material [25 subfolders fastened together]
      - [MCB 324, seminar series], circa 1990-1995
    - Birge, Ray [seminar presenter], undated
    - Correspondence, undated
    - Northeast Society of Toxicology (SOT), 1994-1996
    - Grant files, undated, 1982
      - NIH and UConn Research Foundation awards for "Starvation and Regulation of Protein Degradation,", 1982
      - NIH - Khairallah, "Mechanisms of Acetaminophen Hepatotoxicity"
      - NIH ROI-AM 15919, "Starvation and Regulation of Protein Degradation"
      - NSF and UConn Research Center Proposal, "Nutritional Control of Hepatic Protein Turnover and Autophagy"
    - Manuscript of "Amino Acid Sequence Data Reveals That the 44 kDa Acetaminophen-Binding Protein is a Subunit of Glutamine Synthetase", Bulera et al, undated
    - "Hepatic Amino Acid Compartmentation and Protein Turnover in the Diurnal Cycle of Meal-Fed Rats" - adapted from talk presented at 10th International Congress of Nutrition, Kyoto, Japan, 1975 August
    - "The Role of Hormones in the Regulation of Glycolysis and Gluconeogensis in Rat Liver"; "Regulation of Enzyme Synthesis and Activity in Mammalian Liver - The Hormonal Control of Glycolysis and Gluconeogenesis", undated
    - "Dissociation of the Covalent Binding from the Oxidative Effects of Acetaminophen: Studies Using Dimethylated Acetminophen Derivates", Biochemical Pharmacology, 1987 November
    - "Regulation of Ribosomal Synthesis", undated
  - (Box 4)
    - Course Files, undated
      - "Biochemical Regulatory Mechanisms" [MCB 324] (contained in accordion file labeled "Reg Mech")
      - "Biochem Reg Mechan Lectures" [MCB 324]
      - "Lectures" (2) [contained in "Reg Mech"]
      - "Transcription Lecture and Handouts"
    - Abstracts -- Society of Toxicology, ASBC/DBS, undated
    - Faculty Trustee Dinner, 1984-1989
    - Gilbert, Walter, Harvard University -- correspondence, undated
    - Last Seminar Series Organized for Department, 1995 Fall
    - Manuscript and correspondence with Holtzman, Eric, Columbia University (contains "Quantitative Assessment of the Contribution of Autophagy to Intracellular Protein Breakdown"), undated
    - Unidentified correspondence, undated
    - Pitot, Henry C., University of Wisconsin -- correspondence, undated
    - Research Data, circa 1975
    - Roomi, M.W., Linus Pauling Institute, CA - correspondence, undated
    - Grant Applications, undated
      - Application to UConn Research Foundation: "Are Intracellular Amino Acid Pools Obligatory Precursors for Protein Biosynthesis?", undated
      - NIH and UConn Research Center grants, "Starvation and Regulation of Protein Degradation"), undated
    - Methione Metabolism in Embryos, 1983 July
    - "Effects of APAP Administration On Protein Metabolism in Cultured Mouse Hepatocytes,", undated
    - "Selective Alterations in the Profiles of Newly Synthesized Proteins by Acetaminophen (APAP) and its Dimethylated Analogues: Relationship to Oxidative Stress" (Bruno, et al), undated
    - Academic Press, Inc. Publishers, "Purification, antibody production and partial amino acid sequence of the 58-kDa acetaminophen-binding liver proteins", Toxicology and Pharmacology, 1991
  - (Box 5)
    - Course material, circa 1963-1995
    - Correspondence, undated
    - Grants Material (UConn FRS grants #52158-521530), undated
    - "Interdependence of Dietary Protein & Vitamins in Metabolism: Part V - Relative Influence of Vitamin A & Ascorbic Acid on Protein Depletion & Repletion in Rats", G.C. Esh & Shyama P. Bhattacharya, Indian Journal of Biochemistry, Vol. 4 No.2, 1967
    - Basic Nutrition, circa 1967
    - Biochemical Pathology, circa 1959
    - Dietary Control of Protein Synthesis, circa 1967
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology Research Notebook - Carnitine/Thesis Data, [in file labeled "MIT Days"], 1963 February 25
    - Medical Sciences, circa 1958-1959
    - Phenylalanine Determinations, circa 1961
    - "The Antidotal Effectiveness of N-Acetylcysteine in Reversing Acetaminophen-Induced Heptotoxicity May Involve an Enhancement in the Degradation of Arylated Proteins" (M.K. Bruno et al), undated
    - Northeast SOT 1986 ("Perturbations in Protein Metabolism as an Index of Acetaminophen Hepatotoxicity", M.K. Bruno et al)
    - Photocopy of John Bartalone Poster: "Immunochemical Detection of Acetaminophen-Bound Liver Proteins,", undated
    - Chipman - Correspondence Review Article, (concerning chapter on Mechanisms of Cell Toxicity in Advances In Molecular and Cell Biology), undated
    - "Acetaminophen Toxicity to Cultured Rat Embryos", Benjamin Weeks et al, Teratogenesis, Carcinogenesis, and Mutagenesis, 1990
    - "A Comparison of Proteins S-Thiolated By Glutathione to Those Arylated by Acetaminophen", Ramond Birge et al, Biochemical Pharmacology, 1991
    - Physiological Control of Intracellular Proteolysis by Glutathione, undated
    - "Compartmentation of Free Amino Acids for Protein Biosynthesis," Alda Vidrich et al, Biochemical Journal, 1974
    - "Compartmentation of Free Amino Acids for Protein Synthesis in Rat Liver", Judith Airhart et al, Biochemical Journal, 1976
  - (Box 6)
    - Course evaluation (NUSC 324), 1995
    - Khairallah Biochem 204, 1973 Fall
    - Biol-196 evaluation - Honors Seminar, 1994
    - Cell Culture Facility correspondence, 1982
    - Curriculum committee, College of Liberal Arts and Sciences, 1993 Fall
    - Department meetings and affairs, MCB, undated
    - International Congress of Toxicology - Seattle, 1995
    - Medina, Daniel, Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX, undated
    - "Intracellular 58-kd selenoprotein levels correlate with inhibition of DNA synthesis in mammary epithelial cells", David G. Morrison et al, Carcinogenesis, 1988
    - Nutrition Dept. correspondence, undated
    - International Congress on Toxicology - Seattle Meeting, 1995
    - Things of Interest, undated
    - Wal-Mart Award Correspondence, 1993 Fall
    - "Acetaminophen Binding and Hepatocyte Homeostasis in Toxicity", NIH, PHS grants, 1990
    - "Acetaminophen Covalent Binding and Hepatotoxicity"/"Cellular Responses to Acetaminophen Covalent Binding,", 1991-1995
    - Bromobenzene Grant Write-Up, undated
    - Grants budget requests, circa 1989
    - Grants - rough copies, progress reports, undated
    - Rough Draft of Grant Proposal, Cohen & Khairallah, NIH grant for acetaminophen study, 1996
    - Draft of paper with Gary Ginsberg, "Acetaminophen Hepatotoxicity in Mice: Covalent Binding to and Effects Upon Hepatic Organelles", Gary L. Ginsberg and Steven D. Cohen, undated
    - "The Selective Translocation of the Arylated Cytosolic 58-kDa Acetaminophen Binding Protein Into the Nucleus", Hong et al, circa 1993
    - APAP original graphs [raw data], undated
    - "A Role For Glutathione in Regulating Protein Secretion and Short Term Proteolysis In Hepatocytes", Bruno et al [partial], undated
    - Abstract with Greg Makowski, 1439: "Coordinate Regulation of Hepatic Intracellular Proteolysis With Autophagic Sequestration but Not With Cathepsin B1 Activity", Abstracts, 72nd Annual Meeting of American Society of Biological Chemists, 1981
    - Abstracts Presented at American Society of Biochemistry, Washington, DC, "Altered Patterns of Protein Phosphorylation Following Acetaminophen-Induced Toxicity in Hepatocytes", Bruno et al; "Acetaminophen Administration Alters Rate of Cell Replication In Hepatoma Cells Without Activation of Drug by Cytochrome P-450", Navarro et al, 1994
    - Abstracts of talks presented at different meeting [sic], Sanghani, Hong, et al, undated
    - FASEB Abstract, 4028, "Modal Heptotoxicants Induce the Translocation of the Cytosolic 58 kDa Acetaminophen Binding Protein Into the Nucleus,", 1995
    - Paper with Sid Nelson, "A Comparative Study of Mouse Liver Proteins Arylated by Reactive Metabolites of Acetaminophen and Its Nonhepatotoxic Regioisomer, 3'-Hydroxyacetanilide", Chemical Research in Toxicology, 1994 May
    - "Purification 58 Protein Raw Data", Manuscript and Original Paper; "Purification, Antibody Production, and Partial Amino Acid Sequence of the 58-kDa Acetaminophen-Binding Liver Proteins", Bartolone et al, Toxicology and Applied Pharmacology, 1991-1992
    - Society of Toxicology Annual Meeting abstracts, UConn submissions, 1991
    - "Cellular Consequences of Protein Adduct Formation,", undated
    - Two Chapters: "Acetaminophen, Acetaminophen-Induced Hepatotoxicity" (Toxicology of the Liver, 2nd Edition; Volume IX (of?): Liver and Gastrointestinal Systems, undated
    - Student files, undated
      - Airhart, Judith and Mark, undated
      - Ana Tveit, undated
      - Caryn Navarro, undated
      - Castellani, John, undated
      - Mira Hong, undated
      - Kapferer, Peter, undated
      - Sanghani, Monica, undated
  - (Box 7)
    - Biochemical Regulatory Mechanisms, 1976 Spring
    - Crivello, Joseph, University of California, San Diego, undated
    - Symposium on Protein Turnover & Lysosomal Function: State University of New York at Buffalo, - 'Final Paper Enclosed' (contains "In Vivo Determination of Rates of Protein Degradation in Livers of Meal-Fed Rats: Implications of Amino Acid Compartmentation", Khairallah, 1977 August 21 - 26
    - Department of Molecular and Cell Biology's Space Committee Report, 1985 Fall
    - Department training grant, undated
    - Faculty search -- various correspondence, circa 1970-1988
    - Freake, Hedley C., search candidate, 1987 Spring
    - Nutritional Sciences, circa 1991
    - Photographer, position in Biological Sciences Dept., 1977
    - A.A. Analyser Service, Beckman Amino Acid Analyzer - repairs, funding, undated
    - Crivello, Joseph, University of California, San Diego, undated
    - Electronics Course, 1970
    - 8th International Committee on Proteolysis Conference, 1992
    - Patent for Automated Enzyme Assay Involving Isotope Exchange, 1971-1972
    - "Control of Protein Synthesis in Liver", Jean-Pierre Jost, 1970-1973
    - Correspondence: Dr. Howard G. Worman, Mount Sinai School of Medicine, undated
    - Manuscript: poster presentation materials, A. Tveit, Society of Toxicology conference, 1992
    - "Identification of a 54 kDa Mitochondrial Acetaminophen-Binding Protein as Aldehyde Dehydrogenase", Judith Landin et al, Toxicology and Applied Pharmacology, circa 1996
    - "Identification of the mouse liver 44kDa acetaminophen binding protein as a subunit of glutamine synthetase", Bulera et al, Toxicology and Applied Pharmacology, 1995
    - "Post-Arylative Action of NAC: Degradation of Proteins", in envelope marked "manuscript/final publications/letters from publisher, undated
    - Student files, undated
      - Bulera, Steven J., 1992, 1996
      - Nashanian, Ervant, undated
      - Natarajan, Kartik, undated
      - Navarro, Caryn, 1996
      - Prechek, Derek, undated
  - (Box 8)
    - Lecture -- TP Induction, 1964
    - Biochemical Regulatory Mechanisms - early lectures, undated
    - Calcium In Regulation" lectures notes; course unknown, undated
    - DNA Biology, Biochemical Regulatory Mechanisms, Course material and lectures, circa 1989
    - Cyclic CMP - Seminar and Lecture, undated
    - Early Lectures on DNA Synthesis, undated
    - Estrogen Receptors Lecture, undated
    - Lectures and Course Material, 1970-1973
    - Hormone Transducers, lecture notes/diagrams, undated
    - Lecture and Handouts on Translational Control, undated
    - Material Related to MC324 Biochemical Regulatory Mechanisms, undated
    - MC 349 - Protein Processing Lecture, undated
    - Membrane Recycling Lecture, undated
    - Protein Kinase Lecture, undated
    - Dept. Affairs MCB, 1981-1994
    - Ulla Hansen, Biochemistry search candidates, 1993
    - Various holiday cards, undated
    - Corcoran, George B., University of New Mexico School of Pharmacy, correspondence, undated
    - Dean Jones, Ph.D., Emory University School of Medicine, G. Yost, University of Utah, undated
    - American Society of Cell Biology Meeting, 1990
    - Frank Blood Award, undated
    - Halle Meetings - Meeting Publication & Original Photographs, "Diurnal Variations in Protein Synthesis and Degradation in Livers of Meal-Fed Rats: Implications of Amino Acid Compartmentation", 1977
    - Lanfear/Harrison, P.R., Wolfson Laboratory for Molecular Biology, Glasgow, correspondence re: Carcinogenesis 14:335-340, 1993
    - Tappel, A.L, University of California, Davis, undated
    - Todd Schuster, Biochemistry/Biophysics dept. head, facilities-related correspondence, 1977
    - Yugoslavia and Israel Meetings, 1984-1985
    - Application to NIH for "Acetaminophen Covalent Binding and Hepatotoxicity, 1996
    - Grant proposal to UConn Research Foundation for "Turnover of the 58-kDa Acetaminophen Binding Protein (Emergency Interim Funding), 1991
    - NIH and UConn Research Foundation Grants, 1979-1986
    - NIH funding of "Cellular Significance of the Translocation of the 58-kDa Acetaminophen Binding Protein into the Nucleus,", undated
    - "Actinomycin, Puromycin and Ethionine Inhibition of Synthesis of Gluconeogenic Enzymes in Acute Diabetes," George Weber & R.L. Singhal, Metabolism, 1964 January
    - "Actinomycin: Inhibition of Cortisone-Induced Synthesis of Hepatic Gluconeogenic Enzymes", Weber et al, Science, 1963 october
    - "Activité de treize enzymes du métabolisme intermédiaire, dans le foie du jeune rat qui récupére d'une malnutrition protidique," J. Camus et al, European Journal of Biochemistry, 1969
    - "Asymmetry and symmetry in cellular organization", Heinz Herrmann, Computers and Mathematics with Applications, 1986
    - "Control of protein degradation in muscle by prostaglandins, Ca2+, and leukocyctic pyrogen (interleukin 1)", Goldberg et al, FASEB proceedings, 1984 April